<page>
    <title>1972 New Zealand eight</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>56165816</id>
    <revision>
      <id>818179050</id>
      <parentid>818168634</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-01-02T01:58:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Schwede66</username>
        <id>10689882</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>expand</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{use dmy dates|date=January 2018}}
[[File:August 1971 107 M8+ NZL in lead.jpg|thumb|450px|Semi-final at the [[1971 European Rowing Championships]]; New Zealand is ahead of the Soviet Union and Czechoslovakia]] The '''1972 New Zealand eight''' was a team of [[Rowing at the 1972 Summer Olympics – Men's eight|Olympic gold medallists]] in [[Rowing (sport)|rowing]] from New Zealand, having previously won the [[1971 European Rowing Championships]] in identical composition. At the time, the [[Eight (rowing)|eight]] was regarded as the [[blue ribbon]] class of rowing, and the sport still had amateur-status in New Zealand, unlike many of the other rowing nations that New Zealand competed against. After a disappointing Olympic performance at the [[Rowing at the 1968 Summer Olympics|1968 Summer Olympics]] by the [[Rowing at the 1968 Summer Olympics – Men's eight||New Zealand eight]], national selectors [[Rusty Robertson]], [[Don Rowlands]], and [[Fred Strachan]] were tasked with assembling a new crew. Robertson was also the team's coach. The next time a New Zealand eight competed was at the [[1970 World Rowing Championships]], where they came third. The team was once again significantly changed for the next rowing season, with the [[1971 European Rowing Championships]] and other international regattas beforehand seen as the ultimate test for the [[1972 Summer Olympics]]. The team put up an impressive performance, beat the highly favoured East German eight, and became European champion; at the time the win was regarded to hold world championship status. No further changes were made to the team, not even their seating position, for the 1972 season. Despite a shoe-string budget, financial constraints, and all rowers working part time, the 1971 success was repeated and the [[Rowing at the 1972 Summer Olympics – Men's eight|team won Olympic gold]] in Munich. The president of the [[International Olympic Committee]] (IOC), [[Avery Brundage]], was a zealous advocate of [[Amateur sports|amateurism]]; he was so impressed by the New Zealand performance that he insisted on handing out the gold medals himself.

The team won some significant awards and recognition for its successes. The rules of the &quot;Sportsman of the Year Award&quot; had to be changed so that a team could win the supreme award; this was awarded after their European championship win. Brundage also awarded the [[Muhammed Taher Pasha|Taher Pacha]] Trophy for distinction in amateur sport in 1971. After the Olympic success, the team was again awarded &quot;Sportsman of the Year&quot;; the first time a back-to-back award had been handed out. Rowlands, their manager, was appointed a [[Order of the British Empire|Member of the Order of the British Empire]] (MBE) in the [[1973 New Year Honours]]. Over time, coach Robertson, manager Rowlands, and then the team as a whole were inducted into the [[New Zealand Sports Hall of Fame]].

The most vivid memory by most New Zealanders is not of the Olympic race itself, but seeing the rowers on the victory [[podium]] overcome with emotion and &quot;bawling like babies&quot; when, much to almost everybody's surprise, &quot;[[God Defend New Zealand]]&quot; was played instead of the national anthem, &quot;[[God Save the Queen]]&quot;. It was the impetus for a campaign to make &quot;God Defend New Zealand&quot; the New Zealand anthem, and in 1977 it was gazetted as having equal status to the traditional anthem.

==Background==
There were expectations for the New Zealand eight to win a medal at the [[Rowing at the 1968 Summer Olympics – Men's eight|1968 Summer Olympics]] in [[Mexico City]], but the team came fourth and this was regarded as a failure. The situation was the opposite for the other New Zealand boat in Mexico. The coxed four was technically a spare, the rowers were to have travelled to be available as a reserve for the eight team. The [[Rowing at the 1968 Summer Olympics – Men's coxed four|coxed four]] won an unexpected gold medal.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=50–55}} Getting the amateur rowers to Mexico had required a massive fund-raising exercise and the [[Rowing New Zealand|New Zealand rowing association]]&lt;!-- no idea what they were called at the time, but certainly not yet Rowing NZ --&gt; was in no position to send rowers to any international regattas in 1969, but targeted the [[1970 World Rowing Championships]] in [[St. Catharines]], [[Ontario]], Canada. At the time, the eight was seen as the most important boat class, and three from the Mexico eight trained for the 1970 world championships: [[Wybo Veldman]], [[John Hunter (rower)|John Hunter]], and [[Gil Cawood]]. Members of the 1968 coxed four made another four members: [[Warren Cole]], [[Dick Joyce (rower)|Dick Joyce]], [[Dudley Storey]], and cox [[Simon Dickie]]. The team was complemented by experienced sculler [[Murray Watkinson]] and a young [[Gary Robertson (rower)|Gary Robertson]]. [[Ross Collinge]] from the Mexico coxed four had attended the trials but missed selection. After having won both its heat and the semifinal in Canada (beating the Soviet Union and West Germany in the latter), the boat came third. East Germany dominated, and the Soviet Union was a mere 0.2&amp;nbsp;seconds ahead the New Zealand boat. The team did not gel, and Watkinson's selection became regarded as a mistake; as a single sculler, he had become used to &quot;doing his thing in his own time&quot;.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=56f}}

[[File:Avon River at East Lake 140.JPG|thumb|Rowing club buildings at Kerrs Reach on the [[Avon River (Canterbury)|Avon River]]]]
The officials at the time were [[Rusty Robertson]] as coach, [[Don Rowlands]] as manager, fund-raiser and organiser, and [[Fred Strachan]]&lt;!-- do not even think of removing the red link, as he's notable-as --&gt; as strategist.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=56}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Golden Olympic moments&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Anderson |first1=Ian |title=New Zealand's Golden Olympic moments: Rowing men's eight at Munich 1972 |url= https://www.stuff.co.nz/sport/olympics/nz-olympic-team/81698416/new-zealands-golden-olympic-moments-rowing-mens-eight-at-munich-1972 |accessdate=1 January 2018 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |date=2 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The coach was the uncle of the youngest crew member, Gary Robertson.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=56}} Robertson had been appointed coach in 1967 and it was then that the national training centre relocated from [[Auckland]] to [[Christchurch]], under great controversy. Kerrs Reach on Christchurch's [[Avon River (Canterbury)|Avon River]] was more convenient to reach for [[Dunedin]]-based Strachan than Auckland, and Robertson embarked on a daily drive from [[Oamaru]]—a {{convert|500|km}} return journey–after work whenever there was a training day.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=48}}

==1971 European Rowing Championships==
The [[1971 European Rowing Championships]] were seen as an important stepping stone for the Olympic preparation. The intention was to select a crew and then make minimal changes prior to the [[Rowing at the 1972 Summer Olympics|Munich Olympics]]. At the time, both the [[World Rowing Championships]] and the [[Summer Olympic Games]] were held at four-year intervals, and the annual [[European Rowing Championships]] in the in-between years were regarded as having quasi-world championship status.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=57}} It was decided for Watkinson to revert to single sculls, and for Storey to return to the coxed four. Cawood was no longer available. The three were replaced by three developing rowers—[[Lindsay Wilson (rower)|Lindsay Wilson]], [[Athol Earl]], and [[Trevor Coker]]—and they were teamed with the other young rower, Gary Robertson, to form the bow of the boat. The biggest selection surprise was Earl, as he had just turned 18. But he had been coached by Strachan at [[St. Andrew's College, Christchurch|St. Andrew's College]] in Christchurch and without being personally known to one of the selectors, Earl himself doubted that he would have been chosen ahead of more experienced oarsmen. The experienced rowers chosen for the stern—Cole, Veldman, Joyce, and Hunter—were kept from the previous team. The day before the team was to assemble in Christchurch for their first training, Cole pulled out for family reasons. [[Tony Hurt]] from Auckland was chosen to replace him.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=57f}} Joyce was the initial stroke, but this did not work out. He was replaced by Hurt, and although from a sculling background and, at {{convert|183|cm|ftin}} and {{convert|83|kg|st}} small for a rower, he worked out well for the team. Veldman called him &quot;a brilliant stroke&quot;.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=59}} On Sunday afternoon, the four stern rowers and their bow counterparts would race each other in coxless fours. Dickie recalls that the experienced rowers in the stern had a slight edge, but they did not win every time, and there was great rivalry.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=59f}}

The crew arrived in Europe to find that both their new four and eight Italian Donoratico boats were inferior. Joyce applied his engineering skills and moved all seats backwards, and that improved the boats' performances. Regattas were rowed in [[Duisburg]] and [[Klagenfurt]], and the New Zealanders set new course records at both venues. At the European Rowing Championships venue at the Danish [[Lake Bagsværd]] north of [[Copenhagen]], the favoured East Germans, but also the West Germans, also set new course records in their heat, only to be bettered by the New Zealanders in their heat. In the semi-final, New Zealand faced the Soviet Union, the team that had narrowly beaten them for second place at the 1970 World Championships. Both New Zealand and East Germany won their semi-finals in convincing style. Everything about the East Germans made them the big favourite. They were the incumbent European and World champions, and they had not been beaten in five years since they came together in age-group competitions. They were full-time athletes, nominally employed by the [[Volkspolizei|Police]]. Veldman described them as being like clones, as their rowers were well matched in height and arm length. There were also [[Doping in East Germany|rumours of doping]], something that would not be confirmed in its full effect across all sports until 1993.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=61f}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Ahrens |first1=Peter |title=Doping in der DDR |url= http://www.spiegel.de/sport/sonst/doping-in-der-ddr-susann-scheller-kaempft-gegen-nebenwirkungen-und-fuer-recht-a-1145899.html |accessdate=1 January 2018 |work=[[Spiegel Online]] |date=3 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Golden Olympic moments&quot; /&gt; The race strategy for the Danish final, where the New Zealand eight would meet the favourites East Germany for the first time, was simple: sprint for the first 500&amp;nbsp;m and then somehow hang on to win. Joyce explains that they all knew that if the East Germans would get in front, they'd never get past them again. During the whole race, the New Zealanders were always ahead.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=63}} The New Zealanders won with a time of 5:33.92, closely followed by East Germany in 5:34.32, and the Soviet Union in 5:39.74 well back.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= (M8+) Men's Eight – Final |url= http://www.worldrowing.com/events/1971-european-championships/mens-eight/ |publisher=[[International Rowing Federation]] |accessdate=1 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rowlands saw [[Thomas Keller (rowing)|Thomas Keller]], the president of the international rowing organisation [[International Rowing Federation|FISA]], shed tears of delight.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=63}} [[Avery Brundage]], the [[president of the International Olympic Committee]] (IOC), awarded the team the [[Muhammed Taher Pasha|Taher Pacha]] Trophy (also known as the Mohammed Taher Trophy&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite sports-reference | title = Olympians Who Were Awarded the Mohammed Taher Trophy | url=https://www.sports-reference.com/olympics/friv/lists.cgi?id=118 | accessdate = 1 January 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;) for distinction in amateur sport.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=63}} In November 1971, the team won the &quot;Sportsman of the Year Award&quot;; it is now known as the &quot;Supreme Award&quot; at the [[Halberg Awards]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ODT Halberg&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Meikle |first1=Hayden |title=Sports awards: Five decades of celebrating excellence |url= https://www.odt.co.nz/sport/other-sport/sports-awards-five-decades-celebrating-excellence |accessdate=1 January 2018 |work=[[Otago Daily Times]] |date=14 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rules had to be altered so that the award could be given to a team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Jillings |first1=Kasia |title=Eric Murray &amp; Gary Robertson: Our oarsome double |journal=[[New Idea]] |date=21 March 2013 |url=https://nz.lifestyle.yahoo.com/life/a/16415112/eric-murray-gary-robertson-our-oarsome-double/#page1 |accessdate=23 October 2016 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20161024031010/https://nz.lifestyle.yahoo.com/life/a/16415112/eric-murray-gary-robertson-our-oarsome-double/#page1 |archivedate=24 October 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first time that the award was won for rowing.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=64}}

==1972 Summer Olympics==
[[File:Sylvensteinspeicher 100708.jpg|450px|thumb|In Europe, the New Zealanders were based in [[Lenggries]] and trained on the [[Sylvenstein Dam|Sylvenstein Reservoir]]]]
For the next rowing season, Strachan became manager in place of Rowlands.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=65}} Trials were held in March 1972 in [[Whanganui|Wanganui]], the traditional location for national trials, with the [[Whanganui River]] offering good rowing opportunities. Whilst there was an expectation that the crew was to be kept, there was considerable uncertainty about it and Gary Robertson had already resigned to the doubt that Storey would take his seat before his name got read out.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=64f}} Cole tried to get back into the team but did not manage to unseat anybody; the team remained the same as the one that rowed in the previous year.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=58, 65}} One of Strachan's first tasks was to unite the rowing fraternity at their annual general meeting behind the plan to send an eight to the Olympics. He was given support, but it was mostly left to the team and their organisers to raise the approximately $25,000 needed for the seven weeks in Europe. To keep costs down, Strachan organised for the rowers to stay in the Bavarian town of [[Lenggries]], about an hour's drive away from the Munich regatta course. Whilst there were no dedicated rowing facilities in Lenggries, the [[Sylvenstein Dam|Sylvenstein Reservoir]] provided good training opportunities. Beyond that, the locals were brilliant hosts and many friendships formed at the time.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=66}}

The organisers had again ordered a shell from Donoratico, and they delivered them two boats; one built exactly as ordered, but a second that the manufacturer thought would finally address all the teams' desires. In addition, they had a Karlisch shell built by [[Empacher]] available to them, but it was not well liked. The team preferred the second Donoratico but their coach thought the Karlisch was superior. Again, Joyce was asked to use his engineering skills to make some modifications. A day after he had finished, one of the seats in the Donoratico collapsed and left that boat unusable. From then on, the Karlisch was used.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=66f}}

The first regatta in Germany was a warm-up event at the Olympic rowing course. The New Zealanders, still using their Donoratico, were beaten by the American team. At the next regatta in [[Hanover]], the Americans were beaten by a 2–second margin, and the next day the New Zealanders beat the Australian team (second at the 1968 Olympics).{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=67}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Neuseelands Achter für Olympia gerüstet |url= http://zefys.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/ddr-presse/ergebnisanzeige/?purl=SNP26120215-19720807-0-6-116-0&amp;highlight=Neuseel%C3%A4nder%7CNeuseelands%7CRuder%7C1972%7C08 |accessdate=1 January 2018 |work=[[Berliner Zeitung]] |volume=28 |issue=217 |date=7 August 1972 |page=6 | language=de}}&lt;/ref&gt; A few days out from the Olympics, the sad news was received that Earl's father had died on his way to Munich. Whilst doctors had advised against travel due to a weak heart, his parents went nonetheless and his father died when they were in Italy. Earl still went ahead with the competition, and Strachan remarked later that &quot;he still performed&quot;. The funeral had to wait until the rowers had returned to New Zealand.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=67f}}

When the Olympic racing started, the New Zealanders won their heat comfortably. There was a false start caused by one of the officials, for which the New Zealanders received an official apology – unlike the other crews, they had not heard the recall bell and started racing in earnest. In the real heat, they eased off after the first 1000&amp;nbsp;metres but still won by 11&amp;nbsp;seconds. The semi-final was more of a challenge, with a long delay due to wind that was affecting different lanes with different intensity. The West German crew, the 1968 Olympic champion, had a more sheltered lane and overtook the New Zealand crew at half-way point when the boat was hit by a gust of wind. Robertson, the coach, was livid about the conditions they had to row in, and he decided to knock the other teams' confidence through some mind games. It was announced to the media that the New Zealanders would do some 500&amp;nbsp;metre pieces on the regatta course. It worked, and between 50 and 60 people with stop watches turned up to measure the performance.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=68f}} Robertson explained his strategy in his usual straightforward manner:{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=69}}

{{Cquote|text=We're bloody good and they [the opposition] had better know they [the New Zealand eight] are bloody good, because it's too late for them to do anything about it.|author=Rusty Robertson|source= Reflections of Gold}}

The rowers themselves played their own game. Their apartment in the [[Olympic Village, Munich|Olympic Village]] was near the entrance and other teams had to walk past. The New Zealanders were on a one-can-of-beer-a-day ration and timed drinking those when others teams went past, stacking the empties, and—in typical New Zealand fashion—they went around the village bare feet. The German media soon wrote about the partying New Zealanders, and this evoked a discussion in West Germany how it could be possible for those larrikins to &quot;beat our boys?&quot;{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=69f}}

{{Listen
|filename    = God Defend New Zealand instrumental.ogg
|title       = &quot;God Defend New Zealand&quot;
|description = Instrumental version of &quot;God Defend New Zealand&quot;
|format      = [[Ogg]]}}
The final was rowed on 2 September; an hour earlier, the New Zealand coxless four had won silver. The New Zealand eight dominated its race to the extent that the interesting part was who would take silver and bronze. Four countries battled for the lower medals: East Germany, West Germany, the USA and the Soviet Union. In the end, it came to a photo finish, with the United States declared silver medallist, 0.06&amp;nbsp;seconds ahead of East Germany. For the New Zealanders, everybody was in sync. Veldman later commented that he had had harder races at club level; it was like having &quot;created a big flywheel&quot;.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=70f}} Some of the team later said that their 1971 gold medal win was the &quot;finer display&quot; of their skill.&lt;ref name=&quot;gold in 1972&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Leggat |first1=David |title=New Zealand's Greatest Olympians – Number 7: The 1972 rowing eight |url= http://www.nzherald.co.nz/sport/news/article.cfm?c_id=4&amp;objectid=11683538 |accessdate=1 January 2018 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |date=30 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The outgoing IOC president, Brundage, was not scheduled to present the medals but insisted on doing so.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall of Fame&quot; /&gt; And the most memorable moment was yet to come – the crew standing on the victory dais overcome with emotion and &quot;bawling like babies&quot; is one of New Zealand's most memorable sporting moments.&lt;ref name=&quot;gold in 1972&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall of Fame&quot; /&gt; The occasion was made more poignant by &quot;[[God Defend New Zealand]]&quot; being played rather than the traditional &quot;[[God Save the Queen]]&quot;. This was not yet the New Zealand anthem and it thus contravened Olympic rules. The New Zealand Olympic liaison officer, Hans Lennarz, is credited with having organised this, and it contributed to the emotion of the occasion.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=72}} Collinge was the only one who knew that the new anthem would be played, as he had by chance been in the main stadium when the German army band rehearsed it, but he had chosen not to tell anyone about it.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=73}}  It is often reported that this was the first time that &quot;God Defend New Zealand&quot; was played at the Olympics,&lt;ref name=&quot;Golden Olympic moments&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gold in 1972&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maritime Museum&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Romanos |first1=Joseph | authorlink= Joseph Romanos |title=New Zealand rowing eight team, Munich, 1972 |url= https://teara.govt.nz/en/photograph/37898/new-zealand-rowing-eight-team-munich-1972 |publisher=[[Te Ara: The Encyclopedia of New Zealand]] | accessdate=1 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; even by the book written about the new anthem,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://exislepublishing.co.nz/Hear_Our_Voices-_We_Entreat.html |publisher=Exisle Publishing | first=Max | last=Cryer |authorlink=Max Cryer |title=Hear Our Voices, We Entreat: The Extraordinary Story of New Zealand's National Anthems |accessdate=15 August 2015 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150517051241/http://exislepublishing.co.nz/Hear_Our_Voices-_We_Entreat.html |archivedate=17 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; but this is incorrect. For reasons unknown, both anthems had been performed 20 years earlier—one after the other—in [[Helsinki]] at the medal ceremony for [[Yvette Williams]]' victory in the [[Athletics at the 1952 Summer Olympics – Women's long jump|1952 long jump]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Romanos |first1=Joseph | authorlink= Joseph Romanos |title=Olympic and Commonwealth games – Rowing, athletics and hockey – late 1960s and 1970s at the Olympics |url= https://teara.govt.nz/en/olympic-and-commonwealth-games/page-3 |publisher=[[Te Ara: The Encyclopedia of New Zealand]] | accessdate=1 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The two rowing medals won in Munich made up a large part of the New Zealand team's medal haul. There was only one other medal won in Munich across the 14 sports in which the country competed with 89 athletes, and that was an athletics bronze by [[Rod Dixon]] in [[Athletics at the 1972 Summer Olympics – Men's 1500 metres|men's 1500 metres]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite sports-reference | New Zealand at the 1972 München Summer Games | https://www.sports-reference.com/olympics/countries/NZL/summer/1972/ | 2 January 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the last time an Olympic rowing race was won in a wooden boat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Golden Olympic moments&quot; /&gt; Whilst the previous year, the New Zealanders had left Denmark the day after the competition, this time they stayed on as their competition had been held in the first week of the Olympics. This provided the opportunity to get to know other rowers on a social basis, and the East Germans invited the other medallists to a garden party at their apartment in the Olympic Village. Dickie, a &quot;larger-than-life personality&quot;, was the life of the party and organised drinking games for the three teams.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=74}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Klaus | last=Ullrich |title=Neuseeland- und USA- Achter besuchten die DDR-Ruderer |url= http://zefys.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/ddr-presse/ergebnisanzeige/?purl=SNP2532889X-19720904-0-8-122-0&amp;highlight=neuseel%C3%A4ndischen%7CNeuseel%C3%A4nder%7CNeuseeland%7CRuderer%7C1972%7C09 |accessdate=2 January 2018 |work=[[Neues Deutschland]] |volume=27 |issue=245 |date=4 September 1972 |page=8 | language=de}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The team would never row competitively together after Munich, but they would again win the &quot;Sportsman of the Year Award&quot;; it was the first time that the award had been won twice in a row.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODT Halberg&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|pp=78f}} Hurt retired from competitive rowing, and the others were broken up for different boats. New Zealand did not enter an eight at the [[1973 European Rowing Championships]] in [[Moscow]], but had a coxed four (which included Robertson and Earl) and a coxless pair (including Veldman, who returned with a silver medal).{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=79}} An eight was next compiled for the [[1974 World Rowing Championships]] in [[Lucerne]], Switzerland. Four of the 1971–72 team were included: Hurt, Wilson, Coker, and Earl. The boat won a bronze medal, beaten by the United States and Great Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.worldrowing.com/events/1974-world-championships/mens-eight/ | title = 1974 World Rowing Championships: (M8+) Men's Eight – Final | website = WorldRowing.com | publisher  = [[International Rowing Federation|FISA]] | accessdate = 2 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sport-komplett.de/sport-komplett/sportarten/r/rudern/hst/84.html | title=Rudern – Weltmeisterschaften. Achter – Herren  |trans-title=Rowing – World Championships. Eight – Men |language=de |website=Sport-Komplett.de |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160312075730/http://www.sport-komplett.de/sport-komplett/sportarten/r/rudern/hst/84.html  |archivedate=12 March 2016  |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hurt's recollection of the race is that they were the last boat out, as they weren't ready and still trying to straighten the boat. They never settled properly and thus couldn't catch the leading teams.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=79}}

Subsequent to the 1972 Olympics, a campaign started to make &quot;God Defend New Zealand&quot; the national anthem. It was gazetted as the country's second national anthem on 21 November 1977, on equal standing with &quot;God Save the Queen&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.mch.govt.nz/files/NZ%20Gazette%20Nov%201977%20%28D-0419235%29.PDF |title=Announcement of the adoption of national anthems for New Zealand |date=21 November 1977 |work=Supplement to the New Zealand Gazette of Thursday, 17 November 1977 |accessdate=1 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rowlands, the manager for the 1972 team, was appointed a [[Order of the British Empire|Member of the Order of the British Empire]] (MBE) in the [[1973 New Year Honours]] for services to rowing.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=45861 |date=1 January 1973 |page=35 |supp=y }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1990,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Athol Earl |url= http://www.olympic.org.nz/athletes/athol-earl/ |publisher=[[New Zealand Olympic Committee]] |accessdate=2 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; the team was inducted into the [[New Zealand Sports Hall of Fame]]. The citation reads in part:&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall of Fame&quot;&gt;{{cite web | first=Ron | last=Palenski |title=Eight, 1971–72 |url= https://web.archive.org/web/20150204013230/http://www.nzhalloffame.co.nz/Inductees/E/Eight-1971-72.aspx |publisher=[[New Zealand Sports Hall of Fame]] |accessdate=1 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Cquote|text=Their win, their manner in achieving it and their laid-bare emotion on the victory dais when God Defend New Zealand was played at their Olympic victory ceremony was a seminal moment in New Zealand sport, one of those moments which for years later people can recall as if it was yesterday.|author=Ron Palenski |source=New Zealand Sports Hall of Fame}}

Their coach, Rusty Robertson, and their manager, Don Rowlands, were also inducted into the Hall of Fame.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rusty Robertson |url=http://www.nzhalloffame.co.nz/Inductees/R/Rusty-Robertson.aspx |publisher=[[New Zealand Sports Hall of Fame]] |accessdate=2 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Sir Donald Rowlands |url=http://www.nzhalloffame.co.nz/Inductees/R/Sir-Donald-Rowlands |publisher=[[New Zealand Sports Hall of Fame]] |accessdate=2 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The original intention was to sell the New Zealand boats in Europe before leaving for home, but the historical significance of the Karlisch hull was recognised and the boat returned to New Zealand. It was used by the Auckland Rowing Club as a training boat for many years.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=78}} In 1996, the Karlisch was bought by the Stevenson family and donated to the [[New Zealand Maritime Museum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Karlisch Rowing Eight; Karlisch Germany; 1972; 1996.116 |url= http://www.nzmuseums.co.nz/account/3358/object/2253/Karlisch_Rowing_eight |publisher=NZMuseums |accessdate=1 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maritime Museum&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Untitled |url= https://www.maritimemuseum.co.nz/munich-rowing-eight |publisher=[[New Zealand Maritime Museum]] |accessdate=1 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the boat was owned by the museum, the team members went out for a row on [[Waitematā Harbour]]. Only Coker was missing—he had died in 1981 from a brain tumour—but his son took his place.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=78}}

The eight surviving members of the 1972 team carried the [[Commonwealth Games]] flag into [[Mount Smart Stadium]] at the opening ceremony of the [[1990 Commonwealth Games]] in Auckland.{{sfn|Bidwell|2010|p=77}}

When the [[2007 World Rowing Championships]] were again held in [[Munich]], [[Chris Nilsson]]—who in 1972 had been a member of the [[Rowing at the 1972 Summer Olympics – Men's coxed four|coxed four]] but was by then a rowing coach—arranged for the New Zealand team to stay at Lenggries once more, rekindling old friendships.{{sfn|Stevenson|2016|pp=140f}} In 2008, sports journalist [[Joseph Romanos]] picked the 1972 gold medal win as New Zealand's best ever team performance at the Olympic Games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Romanos |first1=Joseph |authorlink1=Joseph Romanos |title=New Zealand's rowing eight wins gold |url= https://nzhistory.govt.nz/page/new-zealands-rowing-eight-win-gold-munich |publisher=[[Ministry for Culture and Heritage]] |accessdate=2 January 2018 |date=31 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Individuals==
The table below shows the individuals who were involved in the 1971 and 1972 campaigns either as athletes or officials. Two of the officials and two of the rowers have since died. The most recent to die was Dickie in December 2017 amidst the team organising a reunion in conjunction with the next Halberg Awards presentation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Rowing: Double Olympic gold medallist Simon Dickie passes away |url= http://www.nzherald.co.nz/sport/news/article.cfm?c_id=4&amp;objectid=11959119 |accessdate=16 December 2017 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |date=2 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
! Name
! born
! died
! data-sort-type=&quot;number&quot; |role
|-
! {{sortname|Rusty|Robertson}}
| {{dts|1927}} || {{dts|1989}} || {{sort|1|trainer}}
|-
! {{sortname|Fred|Strachan}}
| {{dts|Aug 1923}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=McMurran |first1=Alistair |title=Rowing: No stopping Strachan yet |url= https://www.odt.co.nz/sport/rowing/rowing-no-stopping-strachan-yet |accessdate=2 January 2018 |work=[[Otago Daily Times]] |date=16 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ||  || {{sort|2|manager in 1971}}
|-
! {{sortname|Don|Rowlands}}
| {{dts|17 Jun 1926}} || {{dts|18 Mar 2015}} || {{sort|3|manager in 1972}}
|-
! {{sortname|Gary|Robertson|Gary Robertson (rower)}}
| {{dts|12 Apr 1950}} ||  || {{sort|4|bow}}
|-
! {{sortname|Trevor|Coker}}
| {{dts|1 Oct 1949}} || {{dts|23 Aug 1981}} || {{sort|5|seat 2}}
|-
! {{sortname|Athol|Earl}}
| {{dts|1 Oct 1952}} ||  || {{sort|6|seat 3}}
|-
! {{sortname|Lindsay|Wilson|Lindsay Wilson (rower)}}
| {{dts|15 Oct 1948}} ||  || {{sort|7|seat 4}}
|-
! {{sortname|John|Hunter|John Hunter (rower)}}
| {{dts|8 Nov 1943}} ||  || {{sort|8|seat 5}}
|-
! {{sortname|Dick|Joyce|Dick Joyce (rower)}}
| {{dts|1 May 1946}} ||  || {{sort|9|seat 6}}
|-
! {{sortname|Wybo|Veldman}}
| {{dts|21 Oct 1946}} ||  || {{sort|10|seat 7}}
|-
! {{sortname|Tony|Hurt}}
| {{dts|30 Mar 1946}} ||  || {{sort|11|stroke}}
|-
! {{sortname|Simon|Dickie}}
| {{dts|31 Mar 1951}} || {{dts|13 Dec 2017}} || {{sort|12|cox}}
|}

==See also==
* [[1982 New Zealand eight]]
* [[List of New Zealand rowers at the Summer Olympics]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{cite book |ref = harv | last1=Bidwell | first1=Peter | title=Reflections of Gold | year=2010 | publisher=[[HarperCollins]] | location=Auckland | isbn=978-1-86950-808-1}}
*{{cite book | ref=harv | first=Scotty | last=Stevenson | title=The Kiwi Pair | year=2016 | publisher=[[Penguin Books]] | isbn=978-1-74-348731-0}}

==External links==
*{{YouTube|hmMGnzJjThI}} of the 1972 final
*{{YouTube|yziZDbVLslc}} with 1984 Olympic rower [[Mike Stanley (rower)|Mike Stanley]] citing the 1972 win as what makes him most proud to be a New Zealander

{{S-start}}
{{s-ach|aw}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Harry Kent (cyclist)|Harry Kent]]}}
{{s-ttl | title  = [[Halberg Awards|New Zealand Sportsman of the Year]] | years = 1971, 1972}}
{{s-aft | after  = [[Glenn Turner]]}}
{{s-end}}

[[Category:Rowing teams]]
[[Category:New Zealand rowers]]
[[Category:New Zealand Sports Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:1971 in rowing]]
[[Category:1972 in rowing]]
[[Category:1971 in New Zealand sport]]
[[Category:1972 in New Zealand sport]]</text>
      <sha1>rh24mvf3ro6jky7xjvb6ty5lzd82yt0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>